What’s the best way
to stay healthy
in the face of so much
conflicting nutrition information?
Well, ideally, you would
go to the source.
The gold standard;
the peer-reviewed
medical literature.
Read through stacks of
the latest medical journals.
But who’s got
time for that?
I do!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that plant-based diets
are gaining in popularity among athletes?
In our first story, we discover why
folks are drawn to plant-based diets
for athletic performance and recovery.
Consumer interest in eating
plant-based has surged
over the last few years, and
athletes are no exception.
While in the past, meat was
seen as an irreplaceable
performance-enhancing food,
today the trend is developing
in the opposite direction,
thanks in part to documentaries
like The Game Changers,
for which I was honored to play
a role as scientific advisor.
Several high-profile athletes
from heavyweight champion boxers
to tennis players have
tried fueling with plants.
Athletes have increasingly
been adopting plant-based diets
not only for the
related health beneﬁts
but for perceived improvements
in endurance performance.
In fact, even by 2016, there
were reports of up to a third
of ultra-endurance runners,
for example, shunning meat.
Increasing plant-based foods
may boost vasodilatory—
meaning artery-dilating, antioxidant,
and anti-inflammatory properties
of the diet, which can
lead to improved blood flow,
reduced oxidative stress
and inflammation, and thus,
theoretically enhance
endurance performance,
reduce muscle damage,
and speed recovery.
Exercise itself can release free
radicals that can also lead
to muscle fatigue, reduced athletic
performance, and impaired recovery,
but the antioxidants
concentrated in plant foods
can help extinguish them.
Here’s the level of oxidative
stress before and after running
for a few hours, a doubling of
this oxidative stress marker,
but that’s without blueberries.
Eat a cup and a half of
blueberries an hour before the run
and you can significantly
blunt the stress.
No wonder that eating
even a cup of blueberries
may improve exercise performance,
whereas eating meat could
actually make things worse.
Same with inflammation.
Shifting to a dietary
pattern with more plants
and less animal-sourced food has
been shown to attenuate inﬂammation.
A systematic review and meta-analysis
comparing common biomarkers
of inflammation found
that meat- free diets
appeared to be
favorable in all cases.
And not just inflammation,
but immune status.
Having a strong immune system
is important for athletes,
especially endurance athletes,
as they are often
immunocompromised,
which increases risk of upper
respiratory tract infection.
After a marathon, there can
be about 6-fold higher odds
of coming down with an infection
and after an ultramarathon as
many as 68 percent fall ill
within the ensuing two weeks.
But hey, a better immune system
could translate into less illness,
which means more time training
for the plant-based athlete,
though this has yet
to be studied directly.
We also know there’s an ergogenic,
meaning performance-enhancing,
effect to nitrates, and nitrates
in the bloodstream of vegetarians
is about 20 percent higher
and in vegans 40 percent higher
likely due to their eating
more nitrate-rich vegetables
such as beets, spinach,
and other greens.
And then there are all
the health benefits
that could boost
performance in the long term.
It is well-documented that plant-
based diets reduce the risk
of chronic disease such as
cardiovascular disease, diabetes,
metabolic syndrome, and
cancer and all-cause mortality,
meaning living a
significantly longer life.
But do high-performing athletes
really need cardiovascular protection?
Surprisingly, (and that’s
why I did this video),
endurance athletes may have
more advanced atherosclerosis,
more heart muscle damage,
compared to sedentary individuals.
Male athletes had a higher
percentage of atherosclerotic plaques
in their coronary arteries
compared with sedentary males.
A higher prevalence of
high coronary artery calcium
a greater number of
atherosclerotic plaques
including multi-vessel plaques,
and a greater proportion
squeezing off blood
flow more than 50 percent.
Marathon runners, found
to have increased total
atherosclerotic plaque volume—
calcified plaques,
non-calcified plaques.
Paradoxically, worse atherosclerosis
in their coronary arteries,
which may then translate into more
damage to the heart muscle itself—
three times more than
matched sedentary individuals.
They are running, the risk
of coronary events.
It’s the kind of heart damage
you see after heart attacks.
But wait, why?
Why do studies show that well-trained
athletes are at signiﬁcant risk
for atherosclerosis
and heart damage?
It may not be because
they’re overstressing
their heart with movement
but rather overstressing their heart
with saturated fat and cholesterol.
Endurance athletes can eat
5, 6, 7,000 calories a day.
So, if you’re eating
twice the Big Macs,
no wonder their poor hearts
are getting hammered.
That’s where plant-based
diets come in,
the only diet shown to be
able to reverse the progression
of heart disease in the
majority of patients.
Yeah, such diets may also
contribute to improved performance
and accelerated recovery,
but most importantly,
will allow you to recover and
maintain your long-term health.
Athletic performance
suffers, when you’re dead.
In our next story, we look at the benefits
of reducing acid-forming foods
and boosting alkaline-forming foods.
Theoretically, bathing your muscles in
an alkaline environment should enable
faster acid removal from muscle
cells, delaying the muscle fatigue
that's due to the buildup
of lactic acid in the muscle.
Given these buffering effects,
no wonder sodium bicarbonate —
in other words, baking soda —
has been found to have such
significant ergogenic
or performance-enhancing
effects on muscular endurance.
The problem with loading with
baking soda is that it frequently
causes severe gastrointestinal
distress, and at standard doses
you could easily take in twice the
recommended upper daily limit
of sodium in just that one load.
Therefore, what about a low-acid diet,
which focuses on high intakes
of fruits and vegetables?
That may be an attractive
alternative to bicarbonate loading
for improving anaerobic
exercise performance,
meaning short burst
activity like sprinting.
Today's diets are acid-forming,
meaning higher in animal foods
with fewer vegetables and fruits,
whereas in general, the alkaline-
promoting diet is centered around
whole plant foods, with few processed
foods and less meat, dairy and eggs,
which are accepted as acid-forming
foods. Although alkalizing chemicals
such as sodium bicarbonate have
been shown to consistently improve
performance, alkalizing diets do
not demonstrate the same effect.
A review of ten studies
that investigated
the effect of high versus low dietary
acid loads on athletic performance
did not find consistently improved
exercise performance
at maximal or submaximal
exercise intensities.
However, maybe they just
didn't go alkaline enough?
For example, in this study
they had people eat more
fruits and vegetables
and less meat, cheese,
cereals, and eggs,
but saw no difference in any
performance-related parameters.
But a sufficiently alkaline diet
is characterized by the production
of alkaline urine, a pH
of pee at least 7 or higher.
And if you look at what
the participants achieved,
most failed to meet
the benchmark,
so their diet may just not have
been alkaline-forming enough.
In this study showing enhanced
400-meter sprint performance,
they were able to swap out
enough meat, eggs, cheese
and cereal products, and swap
in enough fruits and vegetables
that they were just barely
able to make 7,
and they did get a little performance
boost, suggesting that it's possible
to improve sprint performance by
consuming alkalizing natural foods
and beverages, without
the ingestion of baking soda.
Thus, an alkalizing diet may be
an easy and natural way
to enhance performance.
However, the performance
enhancement was only about 2% —
just a few seconds.
But check out this study.
The same general strategy:
more fruits and vegetables,
and less the acid-promoting
foods such as meats, cheeses,
and refined grains. But they
weren't messing around.
Six to eight cups of vegetables,
plus more than four
servings of fruit a day, got
their urine up over 7, and a 21%
performance enhancement.
That's extraordinary.
Now this doesn't necessarily mean
it has anything to do with the pH.
I mean they ate more vegetables,
which contain dietary nitrates,
which alone acutely improve
exercise performance.
It's possible that nitrates
might have enhanced
exercise performance
during the low-acid trial.
However, that would entail
extracting more energy
from every breath,
and they didn't find that.
But any time you make huge
changes in peoples' diets,
it's hard to pinpoint exactly what
made the critical difference.
But these extra benefits
are a feature, not a bug.
Because a more alkaline-forming
diet is rich in fruits and vegetables,
and deplete of many unhealthy foods,
a low-acid diet could not only provide
exercise performance benefits, but
might also reduce chronic disease risk.
Any performance benefits
in non-athletes?
The effect of an alkaline diet
on body composition
and aerobic exercise performance
of sedentary women.
A randomized controlled trial,
swapping in vegetable protein
sources like legumes for
animal protein sources, and...
a greater decrease in weight, body
fat mass, lactic acid accumulation,
and perceived exertion levels,
all the while exhibiting a boost
in exercise performance
duration and VO2 max levels,
which is a measure of fitness.
Again pH could just be one of many
explanations why eating healthier
could make you perform
better, but either way
we should recommend athletes
of all ages focus on consuming
ample amounts of fruits and vegetables,
if only to maintain long-term health.
Finally today, we go
back in time, way back,
to compare the diets of the
Roman gladiator “barley men”
to the modern Spartans of today.
Recently, the remains of
dozens of Roman gladiators
were discovered in a mass grave.
The clue to their identities
were the rather distinct types
of mortal injuries they found,
like being speared in
the head with a trident.
Using just their skeletons
they were able to reconstruct
the death blows, show just
how buff they really were,
and even try to reconstruct
their diet of barley and beans.
You can look at carbon isotopes and
see what kinds of plants they ate;
nitrogen isotopes reflect any
intake of animal protein.
You can also look at the
Sulphur in their bones
and the amount of strontium,
leading commentators to submit
that the best athletes
in ancient Rome ate
largely plant-based diets.
Then there were the legionnaires,
the Roman army troopers,
famed for their abilities, also
eating a similar kind of diet,
suggesting “the best fighters
in the ancient world
were essentially vegetarian.”
So, if the so-called
perfect fighting machines,
the great sports heroes of the day,
were eating mostly grains and beans,
should that tell us anything
about sports nutrition
and the preferred diets
of elite athletes?
Well, most of the Greeks and
Romans were basically vegetarian,
centering their diets around
grains, fruit, vegetables and beans,
so maybe the gladiators’ diets
weren’t that remarkable.
Plato, for example, pushed
plants, preferring plant foods
for their health and efficiency.
So yes, the Roman gladiators
were known as the ‘‘barley men,’’
but is that because barley
gives you strength and stamina,
or was that just the basic food
that people ate at the time,
not necessarily for performance,
but because it was just so cheap?
Well, if you look at the modern
Spartans, the Tarahumara Indians,
the ones that run races where
they kick a ball for oh,
75 miles just for the fun of it,
running all day, all night,
and all day, maybe 150 miles
if they’re feeling in the mood.
What do you get if you win?
A special popularity with the ladies
(although how much of a reward
that would actually prove to be
for a man who had been running
for two days straight is questionable;
though, maybe their endurance
extends to other dimensions).
“Probably not since the
days of the ancient Spartans
has a people achieved such a high
state of extreme physical conditioning.”
And what did they eat?
The same kind of 75 to
80 percent starch diet
based on beans, corn, and squash.
And, they had the cholesterol
levels to prove it,
total cholesterol levels down at an
essentially heart attack proof 136.
And it’s not just some
special genetics they have—
you feed them enough egg yolks and
their cholesterol creeps right up.
Modern day Olympian runners
eat the same stuff.
What are they eating over there in Kenya?
A 99 percent vegetarian diet centered
mostly around various starches.
But as in all these cases, is
their remarkable physical prowess
because of their diets, or
in spite of their diets?
Or have nothing to do with their diets?
You don’t know…until
you put it to the test.
In spite of well-documented health
benefits of more plant-based diets,
less is known regarding the effects
of these diets on athletic performance.
So, they compared elite vegetarian
and omnivore endurance athletes
for aerobic fitness and strength.
So, comparing oxygen
utilization on the treadmill,
and quad strength with leg extensions.
And the vegetarians beat out
their omnivore counterparts
for cardiorespiratory fitness,
but their strength didn’t differ.
Suggesting, in the very least,
that vegetarian diets
don’t compromise athletic performance.
But this was a cross-sectional study.
Maybe the veg athletes were just
fitter because they trained harder?
Like in the National Runners' Health Study
looking at thousands of runners:
vegetarian runners were recorded
running significantly
more on a weekly basis;
so, maybe that explains
their superior fitness.
Though, maybe their superior fitness
explains their greater distances.
Other cross-sectional studies
have found no differences
in physical fitness between
vegetarian and non-vegetarian athletes,
or even worse performance, as in this
study of vegetarian athletes in India.
Of course, there could be socioeconomic
or other confounding factors.
That’s why we need interventional
studies to put different diets
to the test and then compare
physical performance,
which we’ll explore next.
In 1896, the aptly named
James Parsley evidently led
a successful vegetarian
cycling club to victory,
their competitors evidently having
to "eat crow with their beef."
Evidently some Belgian
put it to the test in 1904,
with those eating more plant-based
supposedly lifting some weight
like 80 percent more times,
but I couldn't find the
primary source in English.
This I could find though: a famous
series of experiments at Yale,
published more than a century ago, on the
influence of flesh-eating on endurance.
Forty-nine people were compared:
regular athletes (mostly Yale students),
vegetarian athletes, and then
just sedentary vegetarians.
"The experiment furnished a severe test
of the claims of those flesh-abstainers."
Much to the researchers' surprise,
the results seemed to vindicate
the vegetarians, suggesting that
not eating meat leads to far greater
endurance compared to those accustomed
to the ordinary American diet.
Check it out: the first endurance test was
how many minutes straight you could
hold out your arms horizontally:
flesh-eaters versus flesh abstainers.
The regular Yale athletes were
able to keep their hands out
for about 10 minutes on average.
It's harder than it sounds;
give it a try...
OK, but those eating vegetarian
did like five times better.
The meat-eater maximum was only
half that of the vegetarian average.
Only two meat eaters
even hit 15 minutes,
whereas more than two-thirds
of the meat-avoiders did.
None of the regular diet
folks hit a half hour,
whereas nearly half of
the healthier eaters did,
including nine that exceeded an
hour, four that exceeded two hours,
and one guy going for
more than three hours.
How many deep knee
bends can you do?
One athlete could do more
than 1,000—averaging 383—
but they got creamed even
by the sedentary plant-eaters.
That's the crazy thing; even
the sedentary abstainers
surpassed the exercising flesh-eaters.
The sedentary abstainers were,
in most cases, physicians
who sat on their butts all day.
I want a doctor that that can do
a thousand deep knee bends!
And then in terms of recovery, all those
deep knee bends left everyone sore,
but more so among those eating meat.
Among the vegetarians, of two that
did like 2,000 knee bends, one went
straight off to the track to run and
another went on to their nursing duties.
On the other hand, among the
meat-eaters one guy reached 254,
went down once more and couldn't
get back up, had to be carried away,
and was incapacitated for days; another
impaired for weeks after fainting.
It may be inferred without reasonable
doubt, concluded the once skeptical
Yale researcher, that the meat-eating
group of athletes was very far inferior
in endurance to the vegetarians,
even the sedentary ones.
What could account for
this remarkable difference?
Some claimed that flesh foods contained
some kind of "fatigue poisons,"
but one German researcher who detailed
his own experiments with athletes
offered a more prosaic answer.
In his book on what looks like
physiological studies of
uber-driving vegetarians—
I told you I only know English—
he conjectured that the apparent
vegetarian superiority was just due
to their tremendous determination
to prove their point
and spread their propaganda,
so they just make a greater effort
in any contest than do
their meat-eating rivals.
The Yale researchers were worried
about this, and so special pains
were taken to stimulate the flesh-eaters
to the utmost, appealing to
their college pride. Don't let those lousy
vegetarians beat the "Yale spirit."
The experiments made it
into The New York Times.
Yale's flesh-eating athletes—
sounds like a zombie movie—
beaten in severe endurance tests.
Yale professor believes that
he has shown definitely the inferiority
in strength and endurance tests
of meat eaters compared to
those who do not eat meat.
Some of Yale's most successful
athletes took part in the strength tests,
and Professor Fisher declares they
were obliged to admit their inferiority.
How has the truth of this result
been so long obscured?
One reason, Professor Fisher
suggested, is that vegetarians
are their own worst enemy.
In their fanaticism, they jump
from the premise that meat eating
is wrong—often based on scripture
or some kind of dogma—and jump
from that to meat-eating is unhealthy.
That's not how science works
and such logical leaps get them
dismissed as zealots and prevent
any genuine scientific investigation.
Lots of science, even back then,
was pointing a distinct trend
towards more plant-based eating,
and yet the word vegetarian—
even 110 years ago—had
such a bad, preachy rap
that many were loath to concede
the science in its favor.
The proper scientific attitude is to study
the question of meat-eating in precisely
the same manner as one would
study the question of anything else.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.